hello and welcome this is active
inference model stream number 10.1 on
April 4th 2024
4424 and we're really excited today to
be with Bart benp and Albert penko
talking about building a drone with RX
and fur we have an ongoing RX and fur
learning group at The Institute and a
lot of participants have been excited to
use even early versions of this package
and connect it to all the exciting math
and developments so thank you both for
joining looking forward to this very
pragmatic
presentation awesome thanks Daniel
thanks for the kind's words and nice
introduction also welcome everyone
online um as we Daniel mentioned we're
going to build a drone today so last
week I didn't know anything about drones
whatsoever but in the meantime I was
able to craft one with the help of my
colleagues and I want to kind of
transfer the learning experience that I
obtained over this week uh to all of you
such that you can Leverage The Power of
our toolbox RX AER in the end to make
your own very cool applications your own
drone your own autonomous vehicle
whatever you want and we will then be
there also to support you in this
journey but for now let's get started
how are we going to build a drone with
RX infer so first of all let me Bri
briefly introduce myself my name is Bon
Arab I'm a BD student and teaching
assistant in Bap which is the research
group here at inov University of
Technology and together with Albert who
will be Al who's also live uh and we'll
also be monitoring the chat in case
there any questions pop up along the way
we will be your host today together with
Daniel um this talk will be supported by
reactive base so reactive Bas is the
overcoupling getup organization of RX
infer and all the packages on which it's
built at the moment we're looking for
contributors so if you have if you're
interested after this talk please reach
out and then definitely we can uh get
you acquainted with the toolbox and with
our environment
[Music]
there so we're from bias laab the aov
University of Technology we are located
here in aov called city of light and
from here we're doing very interesting
research on building agents probalistic
graphical models and using these to
craft all kinds of engineering
applications trying to solve real world
problems with our
engine our engine RX infer you might
have already heard about this but our
engine um is is a Julia engine which
allows us to perform automatic basan
inference specifically through reactive
message passing the engine that we have
built is completely reative itive which
means that it doesn't do anything unless
there is something to do for it so it's
relatively energy efficient because it
doesn't consume energy uh during all the
other moments and we perform message
passing but I'll give a more in detailed
discussion on this more explanation will
follow later in the
stock and we're going to use this
toolbox in order to craft a drone a
drone that can actually fly using some
simplified drone mechanics go from
position a to position B and I'm very
eager to show you how this journey how
this development Journey looks like so
let's get
started so what I'm going to talk about
are three parts basically in this do I'm
going to first start off with the model
specification so in the basan inference
methodology the first part is always
that we need to craft a model and this
model will include some drone physics so
I'll the take you back to high school
where you learned all these Concepts
refresh a couple of them and based on
that I'm going to construct a generative
model of how a simplified drone would
look like furthermore I'll then continue
upon the probabilistic inference so if
we have crafted this model and we want
this model actually to do something
inference allows us to compute
posteriors in this model and the
inference on this model is actually the
underlying control algorithm that we
will be crafting and this will be
automated using our toolbox RX Ander
then finally we'll wrap up with some
experiments and then there will be
plenty of time uh to answer any
questions that you might
have let's get
going for the model specification we're
going to start off with some simplified
drones physics there will be very easy
for some a refresher for others but
hopefully throughout this uh throughout
these following couple of minutes you'll
have a basic understanding of how a
drone works we have greatly simplified
it because of course going into the
details of three uh three-dimensional
drones with wind all that kind of stuff
would be a bit too much for just a
single live stream but we hope to offer
you the tools and maybe the Machinery to
create these more complicated models
yourself so we have this very nice drone
here and what we're interested in is
what forces act on this drone so we're
going to simplify this a bit and we'll
say that each of the rotors so the left
and the right rotor produce some kind of
upward Force pulling this drone from the
from the
ground of course we also walk around on
Earth and we know that there is also a
force that opposes this namely gravity
which tries to pull us to the ground
well combining these two forces allows
us to either increase or decrease the
altit altitude of this drone and make it
Fly that's the entire
goal in the end the goal will be to come
up with these forces these FL and F FR
such that our drone flies from location
a to a location
B if we do the computations a bit and
see what are the kind of the net force
forces acting on this drone is in this
case we see that we have a vertical
component F1
which is the sum of the individual
forces created by the motor minus the
force of gravity that's acting upon the
Drone and in the horizontal Direction
because everything is nicely aligned we
have a net force of zero if there would
be wind for example there would be a
contribution there but in the simplified
model I assume that well there is no
horizontal component as of
yet but if we tilt the Drone a bit with
a certain angle Theta we actually see
that this Theta not only affects of
course the horizontal um or the vertical
net force but also the horizontal one so
based on this we can obtain
equations for this horizontal and
vertical force acting upon the
Drone the motors we assume that they are
at a distance r a radius are from the
center of mass so we very simplistically
assumed that the center of mass of the
Drone is at the radius R from its rotor
so the force you can think of it as
acting upon an arm creating a specific
moment so the torque that's gets
generated by these rotors with respect
to the center of mass of the Drone is
the difference between these two forces
multiplied with with the radius
r with these three equations so the net
force is acting upon the Drone and this
net torque that we can compute based on
the rotation that the Drone wants to go
to we can already construct a lot big
part of the model of this
[Music]
drone so these are kind of the forces
that we that act upon the Drone
horizontal vertical Direction the
rotation is given by this
torque and we want to convert these
forces into motion because in the end we
want to move the Drone and we want to
figure out what forces are required to
move from a position a to a position B
using Newton's law we can already know
that our force is equal to our u a mass
multiplied with our
acceleration in other words our
acceleration is our Force divided by our
Mass So based on the net forces that we
just computed we can also extract
equations body accelerations in the
vertical and horizontal
[Music]
Direction these accelerations accumulate
so if we integrate over them we get
actually a
velocity so an incremental change in our
velocity you can think of is actually
this acceleration times this incremental
change in time which gives us kind of a
relationship so if we increase the
acceleration over period of time then we
also know that that will lead to an
increase in our velocities in both the
horizontal and vertical
direction if we take this even a step
further is then we can also start to
model the actual position of the Drone
so integrating over this velocity will
give us our position in both the X and Y
[Music]
Direction basically every Small Change
in X will be a result of the particular
velocity over a small period of time and
with this set this this set of equations
it actually becomes possible to extract
the movements from these net forces of
the
Drone so that's basically the movement
so how it moves from left to right up
and down but there is this additional
component to the Drone namely its angle
because its angle also
changes the acceleration in the angle so
the angular acceleration Alpha here is
the torque divided by the moment of
inertia of the Drone you can think of
this as being very similar to Newton's
equation with the forces and the mass
which give us the horizontal or vertical
acceleration but this is just the
similar uh similar equation that's used
for actually angular
acceleration similarly we can also
compute the angular velocity so Omega
because of small increment in this
angular velocity will be our angular
acceleration times a small fraction of
time so integrating over the angular
acceleration will give us the angular
velocity and you might have already
guessed this based on this we can also
compute a new angle so the angle is this
velocity integrated over
time very similarly as we derived the
equations for the actual movement of the
Drone
and together these net forces these
equations for the movement of the Drone
and these simplified equations for the
rotation they constitute the Drone
Dynamics so it might have seemed like a
recap from high school but for the
simplified example this is all that we
actually need in order to craft this
drone and that's what I'm going to show
you right
now because these equations of motion
I'm going to write down in a function
specifically a Julia function because
that's the language that RX infer also
uses on the
hood so we're going to create this
function f and I'm going to walk you
right through it there are just 15 lines
of code so I think this should be
manageable so we have a function f which
accepts the state so you can think of
this state as the positions velocities
angle and angular velocities of the
Drone uh the actions to which we refer
to the forces on the left and right
rotor the particular drone like what are
the characteristics of that drone and
the environment so are we on Mars are we
on Earth all those attributes that are
um environment
related so in the first three lines what
we're going to do is we're going to
extract some information so we're going
to extract the forces from our actions
we're going to extract the mass the
moment of inertia and the radius
of the Drone because these are
properties that correspond to the
particular drone that we're using and
the gravity we're going to just grab
from our environment because if we would
be on Mars we would have very different
dynamics of
course then from the state what we
extract are X and Y which are vertical
or horizontal and vertical
positions VX and VY which are velocities
in the horizontal and vertical Direction
Theta which was our angle and Omega
which was our angle angular
[Music]
velocity with all these properties
characteristics and States extracted we
can actually start implementing the
equations that we have on the left so FG
which is the force generated by the
gravity is simply equal to the mass
times the gravitational
constant FY and FX are merely copied
from the equations on the left so it's
the sum of the forces multiplied with
coine or sign of the angle and for the Y
Force the net y Force we also subtract
the gravity because there it has an
influence and for the net torque we do
the similar so we extract the difference
between the force generated by the left
and right rotor and multiply that with
the radius in order to get us a
torque then next up is we can based on
these forces we can compute the
accelerations in the X and Y Direction
so F ofx / M will give us these
accelerations or F of Y id M for the
vertical
acceleration we're going to take a very
Cru Oiler approximation so we're going
to do a linearization in order to
actually create a new velocity so VX new
which will be the velocity after
enforcing the actions will be our
previous velocity plus our acceleration
times this increment in in time this D D
and this DT we said beforehand but this
is a simplified assumption which of
course there are more
complicated assumptions to be made we
could choose uh oil Marana and all those
other fourth order approximations but
for now let's keep it simple and let's
stick to this very simple order
approximation then based on the
velocities and accelerations we can also
do a similar trick for the new positions
so how does our X and Y coordinate
change based on their previous
coordinates the velocities that we had
at the previous moment and the
accelerations that we
computed here we have this quadratic
term over the
accelerations uh which are merely a
matter of fact of the approximation
because we over DT we also want to kind
of integrate over the accelerations so
that's ODS um the second term basically
ODS for this effect and makes it a bit
more realistic
with that out of the way we can do
similar things for the rotation so the
acceleration the rotational acceleration
is our torque divided by our moment of
inertia that we got from the
Drone we again can update the angular
velocity based on its previous angular
velocity the acceleration that we just
computed and the time
interval and based on that we can also
update our angle
so what this function does it accepts
the state actions and some
characteristics of the Drone in the
environment and some discretization over
time and it computes and returns a new
state so if we would have applied a
specific action of force FL and F FR
corresponding to the two rotor engines
what would be the new state or
approximately the new state that we end
up with it's very simplified but this
you can think of as a state transition
function
with it out of the way now it's actually
time to start with the easy work because
we have now this function f and this
function f specifies how we think this
internal state of the Drone evolves over
time something I forgot to mention but
Julia also supports Unicode so the
people who are paying attention might
have already seen it I still think it's
a great feature but you can actually use
Greek symbols which makes this
translation going from physics to code
way more easy and also allows you to
retain this physical interpretation to
it but that being said let's continue
with the proper model so just remember
now that we have F which en codes our
state
[Music]
transition for our drone we're going to
construct a generative model and here I
have drawn it as a so-called for St
Factor grow but I'm going to talk you
right through it
so what we have is these boxes and these
boxes correspond to factors or functions
on how variables relate to each other
which one relates to another one and how
are they interconnected through which
functions and through um through which
nodes let's say and the edges so the
arrows here in this case correspond to
the individual variables in our
model the variables s in this example
correspond to the state of the agent so
that contains the position of the agent
in both x
y and the velocities also in the XY
Direction furthermore this state also
contains the angle and this angular
velocity to make life a bit
[Music]
simpler u in this case corresponds to
the actions so the actions that we want
in the end to also
[Music]
infer based on this figure we can for
example see around this function f which
was our state transition that we put in
a previous state and the actions and we
get something
out to that we add a bit of gausian
noise to accommodate for any
uncertainties that are maybe in the
parameters in the um in the environment
because we use simplified drone physics
maybe we want to add a bit of process
noise there just to accommodate for the
fact that these Dynamics are not perfect
and that there will always be internal
ex external fluctuations that drive this
drone if we write this down in a
probalistic matter we can construct this
particular Vector graph where we have
these time slices which repeat over time
and mathematically we can write that as
in the equation that's on the slide so
we have a prior on the initial state
which we refer to as P of s0 which
encodes our starting position starting
ities starting
angles and all the way at the end of the
model we have our goal prior so P of s
where capital T promotes the length of
our model also known as our
Horizon this P of St describes okay
where do we actually want the agent to
go what do we want its velocity to be at
the end what do we um want this angle to
be at the end all these kind of
things so together P of s0 and P of St
these two priors the enode the starting
and end position of our drone
respectively whereas this middle part
with the F function the transition
function that we just
described and the control U of which we
can put a gion prior because we want to
infer it together these encode the
Dynamics of the Drone the generative
model how does this this look like I'm
just going to Port it directly into RX
infer so over the past couple of months
with our colleagues have spent um
significant amounts of time actually
improving our modeling language which
makes it now even easier to craft your
own probalistic modelss in RX infer and
with these effectively four lines five
lines of code we can construct the model
the graph that we have on the
left so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to talk you through it and I think
at the end I think hope all questions or
I I don't think there will be a lot of
questions surrounding this particular
model any longer because it's merely a
replication of what's on the left we're
going to Define this variable S1 and S1
in this case actually refers to the
first state but judia indexes with one
so that's why it's not S zero but S1 in
instead and S1 which is our encodes our
starting position we're going to encode
that with a multivariate normal
distribution which main which mean is
given by some initial state that we
provide to the function and which
covariance Matrix we assume to be very
narrow because we assume that we know
the position of the drone at the initial
time
step then inside this for loop we're
going to basically unroll this middle
segment of the Drone
of this generative model we're going to
create a prior on the control so on this
U
oft and we're going to put there Al
multivariant normal because that's nice
to work with w mean is the mass times
gravitation constant divided by two and
then as a vector of two the reason for
this is because our prior Assumption of
this drone is that it exerts a force
because we think it's it's flying
so it would make sense that we assume
the force of the engines will be just
enough maybe to balance the Drone in the
air so this mg ided by two which is
actually the force of the left and right
rotor
respectively they compensate for the
force of gravity if the mo if the engine
or the Drone were to be
upright so here we provide some
additional information that allow us to
imp improve convergence and improve also
estimation because we know that the
Drone is probably not going to drop out
of air we want it actually to kind of
stabilize and stay at its position so we
do that here by putting this prior on
the
control then following that is our state
transition so how do we think our state
evolves over time and this is where the
Dynamics of the simplified run that we
talked about on the previous slide
actually come into play so the mean of
the next state will be given by this
function f over the previous state and
the corresponding actions and the Drone
the environment and the discretization
over
[Music]
time together with some noise because of
the unknown Dynamics maybe we've got
some internal external fluctuations
uncertainties stochastic Behavior so
that's all something that we also encode
in this multivariate normal
distribution so that incorporates this
for Loop and that this for Loop
basically unrolls this segment that's on
the left containing this P of U this F
and this
Norm then finally we finish up our model
by putting this goal prior at the end so
at the Horizon plus one because of the
indexing we're going to put the
multivariate normal whose mean is
located at the goal containing our goal
position goal the velocities that we
wish to attain at the goal um the angle
at goal etc
etc and together these couple lines of
code effectively they're just five they
create the generative model that's on
the
left so that's great we have crafted a
model of how we think the Drone evolves
over time we have derived some
simplified equations to model it states
Dynamics and now we want to do inference
so we are interested in Computing the
marginal distributions over both actions
and States basically we want to ask our
model okay it's nice that you have
encoded this starting and end position
in the model but in order to obtain that
how can we actually reach that how can
we actually do that so we're interested
in figuring out what is actually the
marginal distribution over the actions
so this Q of
U and what is the marginal distribution
over the states so what forces do we
need to apply to go from position a to
position B and how will this trajectory
going from A to B look
like in the general case if we were to
just try to solve this equation and
compute these marginal distributions
then we would have to integrate over all
other
parameters but that's very
computationally heavy because there are
a lot of parameters in a model so doing
this in a naive way would not be
efficient at
[Music]
all but there is luckily a way to make
it efficient namely through message
passing so let's dive a bit deeper into
how that actually looks
like so for this purpose I've created
this simplified factorized model to make
sure everyone can kind of follow along
so we have the different factors fa FB
FC and
FD each link to some of the variables
from X1 ranging to
X6 and and each Vector is only connected
to the variables to which it also
relates it's a simple case
right suppose now that we wish to
compute the marginal here over the
variable
X4 doing this naively would require us
to integrate out this factorized model
over all variables X except for
X4 however that's computation yav as I
mentioned earlier because we have
variables to integrate over and that
might be a challenge because we're in
this very high dimensional space
then luckily what we can do is we can
make use of that these factors are not
connected to everything so the factor
nodes that are on the left are not
connected to each of the variables and
this turns out to be very beneficial
from an efficienty standpoint so we can
effectively split up this large
integration
over the entire model FX into a set of
smaller
integrals simply by making use of this
distributive property of integration
where we can kind of separate them out
put some parts into brackets and by
doing so this large integration problem
actually reduces into a couple smaller
integration problems which are more
efficient to
solve we can also give an interpretation
to this for for example this
fa of X1 X2 integrated over the variable
X1 you can also think of this as closing
the book as we demonstrate on the left
over that factor F
fa and this is the result of this we
call a message so this message you can
think of as a summary of a particular
part of that particular graph of part of
the
graph and we can iterate this a couple
of times so this message mu of X2 if we
propagate that into the next node this
FB and we solve the corresponding
integration with this double integration
over now X2 and X3 we get a new message
mu of
X4 and we can do this this on all the
edges and all the over all the factor
nodes here in our model we can integrate
over the single node FD over the Lo FC
where we have an incoming message mu of
X5 and what we end up with and that's
the interesting part is that all these
messages are relatively easy to compute
they are relatively small because they
do not require this huge
[Music]
integration the funny thing here is is
that this marginal the one that we're
interested in this Q of X4 is now simply
the
product of mu of X4 * the other mute so
the messages that are actually colliding
on that edge and then of course
renormalized but that marginal
distribution can simply be computed on a
very local level by multiplying the
messages that are flowing over these
edges hence making it very efficient to
solve this integration problem and this
is also how we actually solve inference
in our toolbox so in the probalistic
generative model that we created for the
Drone
we can use message passing to solve this
marginal
marginalization in a very efficient
manner to give you an example these are
some benchmarking results that we
obtained with RX infer on the left you
can see how long it takes for a simple
stage based model which is similar to
the model that I've shown before uh but
you can think more of this like in a
common filter setting for people who
have a bit familiarity with Control
Systems uh and we can see that the
filtering and the smoothing both scale
very well they scale very nicely in the
number of observation or in the length
of the model on just linearly
basically on the right we also do a
comparison between RX and fur so R
toolbox and churing churing is another
toolbox in judia which doesn't use
message passing to solve the actual uh
marginalization problem but instead it
reverts to sampling so instead of
computing everything kind of
analytically or mostly analytically or
with approximations it draws a lot of
samples and tries to extract statistics
from this but as you can see the left
axis is on the loog scale so we obtain
significant performance improvements in
comparison to the sampling based methods
and that's also why we are pushing for
our iner because it's just way more
efficient to perform these competitions
with message passing in comparison to
sampling based
methods there is one thing in our model
so if you recall these drone Dynamics
then our state transition was quite
nonlinear so it was very challenging or
it is very challenging to do exact
message passing with this nonlinear
note because if we go from the previous
state to the next state then the
distribution of this next state will no
longer be nice and gaan but it might be
uh distribution which is outside of the
EXP the distribution or the outside of
the family of
exponential distributions let's
[Music]
say so it requires some approximations
in order to actually do inference around
it so in the experiments I have used
unscented which we can just specify with
a little code block on the right and
what this does it draws a very small but
very informative set of samples around
the incoming cauan
distributions which capture the first
and second moment of the distribution so
the mean and variances of these Sigma
points these samples these are still the
same as the statistics of the incoming
normal
distribution what we then do is we use
these very carefully select samples to
propagate throughly
nonlinearity and based on the
transformed Sigma points we then
reconstruct what the gion at the output
could have looked
like so this unscented allows us to make
approximations uh through this
[Music]
nonlinearity with that in place we can
actually perform
inference so the code block on the left
bottom is all you need in order to get
the Drone running so inside the infar
function we specify a model which was
the Drone model that we specified in one
of the previous slides we specify its
data although it's not observing
something directly and it's more doing a
planning task we can still Supply it
with the initial State and the goal
state where do we want the agent to move
to and this meta object corresponds to
the approximations that we wish to
take and that's all that's that's all
that's necessary in order to actually
get this drone up and running and in
order to demonstrate this we have a very
nice experiment created by Dimitri one
of our
colleagues where we have this drone
moving around it will be it's more
complicated than or I would say the
plotting is more complicated than what
I've shown on the previous slide because
actually getting this plotting to work
requires way more code than actually
getting our INF to
work uh but what it allows us to do is
not only to do this planning but also to
do this really in an online manner so
here in this particular example we have
created this uh this video where on the
Fly we are changing parameters so we're
increasing the mass of the Drone making
it heavier we're increasing the size of
the Drone U so it's radius it's engine
power like what are the limits of this
uh this drone what can it L gravity
perhaps you want to move to another
planet and test your simulation there
but we're changing these characteristics
on the Fly and with RX you're still able
to process kind of this do this planning
task that being said
um all the code and the example that I
showed you today they are publicly
available on the reactive base
organization so in the RX for
examples. repository you can find the
code um code required to run actually
the Drone experiment it will be a
simplified experiment so not the one on
the previous slide because that would be
way too intense to over that would be
just too overwhelming to have a look at
but the main characteristics of this
particular drone demo are available here
and if you have any questions want to
try it out please let me know after
um or contact me if you have issues um
but the code that we developed for this
particular live stream is actually
publicly
available and with that I would like to
thank you of course for this very nice
opportunity for this nice
audience um if you want to have more
information feel free to reach out to
any one of us reactive base file issue
whatever you've seen uh deem pretty
can contact us research group bias laab
our spin-off lace Dynamics for
industrial applications but most
importantly for reactive base I want to
say that we also looking for
collaborators so if you got motivated by
this star got inspired to create your
own cool
applications please reach out to us and
hopefully help us develop our ex infer
into the toolbox of the future think
that's something that I would like to
strive for so if you're in inspired
reach out and we'll make sure that there
are amazing opportunities lying
ahead and that's all thanks a lot for
the
attention and I hope it was an inspiring
talk that got you engaged with ARX and
fur got you
excited so uh if you have any questions
please let me
[Music]
know awesome thank you
very cool
presentation Albert do you want to give
any first or overview remarks and then
Chris and kopus we can discuss and ask
some questions
too uh well not not really in a sense
that yeah it was although it was the
first time I saw this presentation it
was uh great B I mean I I knew the the
underline project behind that and how
the Drone works but the presentation I
think was very nice to also connect how
uh while the bean inference is basically
how is it connected to the gold driven
Behavior I think it's um it's really
cool um yeah I just wanted to add along
the presentation that Bart was speaking
about this noise component when he drew
when he has drawn the graph so this
noise component also could be seen as
basically the the compensation for our
poor approximation of the Dynamics right
because we use this first order linear
approximation and well that's arguably
not not the best uh way of approximating
the underlying physics although it
worked for the simplified demo and there
well I think I can just maybe add on how
this demo can be extended or this model
can be extended um well the first thing
to do is well just to use a different
approximation right uh that that's uh
one thing that comes to my mind um and
another thing would be and I think from
the active inference perspective uh
would be to Omit some of the parameters
in the transition function deem them
unknown and to let the agent figure out
it uh through the interaction with the
environment so you could achieve that
also with um AR infer by putting some
priors on the on the metrix or putting
some prior on the components of this
metrix and you can um see how fast the
agent actually learns the physics of the
environment
yeah awesome I'll ask some quick
questions from the live chat and then
Chris and kobus if you want to ask feel
free okay so Carlos asks is the reactive
part based on events to trigger the
pipeline or based on
signals
yeah yeah go ahead Bart yeah so was we
or what Dimitri did when he build it
when he started building this RX infer
toolbox uh um is he used a very
different Computing Paradigm so normally
you execute code from the top to the
bottom but what he did is he used this
reactive Paradigm So based on events a
particular computation is
being executed and these events can be
various it can change of course it
depends very much in the context what an
event is but often the event corresponds
to making actual
observations so especially for active
inference agents if we make a new
observation only then recomputations are
being executed so basically the entire
algorithm does nothing unless there is
something to compute and I hope that
kind of answers the question but I'm not
entirely sure
so if I was a bit unclear maybe Albert
you can uh out to it if you have a
better yeah I'm just not I'm not sure
which kind of reactive part was uh was
meant in in the question because yeah
there is the reactive part of the
inference but also the demo itself was
reactive right like when you are
triggering this but but basically
speaking about how how it works indeed
it it it the it Triggers on the event
basically so and the event is that yeah
something there are few things that
could be changed right it's either
environmental change something changed
in the environment uh and then we we
sense this uh from from our sensors and
then the inference follows right so
there is uh just to add upon what BART
said about this U reactive part so
message passing is wellknown algorithm I
mean it's it's it's been around uh since
Pearl belief propagation perhaps later
earlier but then uh the reactive is is a
particular implementation of this
message passing which is uh more more
kind of uh driven by how the the the uh
the system should work in the field uh
yeah awesome yeah with Magnus kudal we
explored a lot of the message passing
talked a little bit about how all the
messages could be passed at once or the
reactive Paradigm where you could
uncouple the rates of updating um okay
I'll ask one more question from the live
chat and then Chris oropus Fraser asks
fantastic stuff double exclamation point
uhoh if somebody wanted to help develop
RX and fur with your organization what
are the ideal characteristics and
backgrounds to
have I think we are very open so also
within our lab uh in BIOS we have a huge
variety of backgrounds range from
computer science to physics electrical
engineering for myself for example so
there is a wide variety of backgrounds
um possible of course we assume that or
we would like coding to be something
that you're good at or willing to learn
um because I think that's one of the
most important things of course to
develop a software engine and all the
rest I think we can provide you with
excellent materials to get crossed or to
uh to get familiar with the methods that
we use or get acquainted with the models
that we uh that we have developed in the
past
so personally when I started in in this
group and when I started working on this
project I also didn't have any
background so I used to be an electrical
engineer I never heard about well I was
thought probability Theory and then
quickly forgot about it um so my
background was very different and it is
maybe a bit difficult to get started
directly with all this probably message
passing and all this entire Paradigm but
it's definitely a very nice ride to
learn so I would say
um if you're willing to learn willing to
make a nice contribution then that's
always
welcome yeah yeah I well we are mostly
writing stuff in in Julia right so Julia
is uh sort of I mean I mean it's
learnable language right it's not like
if you don't know Julia you can't uh
help us no that's not absolutely not
true so we we welcome uh people from
different programming backgrounds uh and
besides there are different branches on
how you can help within this ARX in
ferent basically the whole reactive base
ecosystem because it cons consists not
only of the inference engine which I
must say it's the most difficult part
for contributing because there are many
intricacies uh involved that uh with
within this uh inference language but um
there is also graph PPL right there is
also rocket there are other U packages
which uh which basically constitute the
whole ecosystem and uh yeah well you you
don't have to be an expert in basian
inference to contribute to Rocket uh or
you don't have to be again um an expert
in particular approximations to
contribute to model builder so and of
course uh documentation is something
which is uh which always needs uh uh an
update right so we we don't dismiss
people for
contributing to the documentation that's
extremely important uh for the for the
community and for ourselves because we
we can see okay so
uh where are the parts which we could
explain better or actually improve our
ecosystem awesome
Copus ah very interesting talk thank you
very much um I have a question about uh
categorical examples where the the
control space consists of values uh from
a categorical
distribution um so does orx infer have
any such examples
available we do we do so we do not only
support continuous variables in this
case but we also support a variety of
category um Renity distributions uh
categorical distributions themselves uh
we do have a lot of examples so if if
you visit the website RX
in.ml there is this huge list of
examples use cases uh some of which
feature categorical distributions as
well modeling is yeah all the ranging
from modeling and simple coin tools to
more advanced examples but we do offer
functionality in both the discrete
domain as in the continuous
domain yeah okay
thank yeah go ahead go ahead now I just
wanted to add there is well most uh kind
of famous example on on or hello world
examples into the categorical world
within I
think is is hidden Market model and I
think we have an example on that I'm not
sure that we have uh Incorporated the
control within that uh example that's
probably learning the transition
matrices for observations and the and
the well the hidden State um but uh
there is I think nothing stopping you
from introducing the control for a for a
certain uh discrete type of uh Mark
model uh thank you and then um I use vs
code um but I do have problems with
Greek symbols uh when they contain
multiple characters in a superscript for
subscript for example so do you guys use
V code at all and if so do you have a
best practice uh to to solve my
problem we do use vs code I think our
entire lab uses FS code because it has
turned out to be a very very nice tool
so it's good that you mention this um
regarding the subscripts and the
superscripts that you mention is
personally I try to avoid them because
often times I completely agree that it
looks nice to have this dot over a
variable for example to the note der
ative or to draw kind of the index with
a
superscript but personally to me that
clutters it a bit and also makes it more
challenging to edit
so I just try to refrain from using sub
and super scripts in vs codes with this
Auto tab although it looks very cool and
might be nice for like demo purposes for
actually experimentation or development
I always try to avoid
them so not a solution but uh this is my
kind of my take on
it okay yeah I can understand uhh yeah
because and another possible problem
with super and subscripts is they can
appear very small and I often find
myself having to zoom in a bit to you
know discriminate between certain
symbols and then my final
question uh to what extent can you guys
parallelize within RX in fur are there
op is low hanging fruit choices to to
apply
parallelization in RX
infer yes so um it's good that you
mention this because at the moment we
have actually a master student who is
kind of working on this particular or
trying to work on this project uh where
we try to parallelize the message
passing and the computation for example
of the marginals so there are
opportunities there to do some sort of
parallelization
um in general at the current moment our
message posting is all linear
unfortunately however there have been
papers where they also paralized that
although it seems that it's impossible
to do apparently it still is uh but
that's something perhaps for a future
project so at the moment we do not
provide a lot of parallelization around
RX and fur but in the future this is
definitely on top of our agenda to make
also improvements in terms of
performance and in computational speed
please um just one quick question please
um another one um have you guys thought
approaching uh big players like Amazon
web services for example to uh you know
and present this to them and try and get
them to incorporate it into their S
tools we have been um so with L Dynamics
kind of the spin-off company which also
uses RX Ander to develop real
application let say for customers we
have considered this this option um but
at the moment we have not been in
contact to any of these these companies
or
clients
um sorry no I just wanted that to we we
haven't talked to none of uh Fang uh so
that's that's uh yeah we haven't done
yet although we are we are we in talks
there are a few interested parties in
the pipeline but uh no we have
approached Amazon no not
yet
excellent thank you Kus I'll ask another
question in the chat and then Chris if
you have anything Fraser asks what are
the largest current challenges to the
reactive message passing Paradigm for
doing this kind of approximate basian
inference it's a very good question I
think it also depends a lot on who you
ask this question to to me personally
um the message passing I think is a
great method in itself and it also
overcomes already a lot of challenges
what I think would be the most
fruitful next step is to really start
working on the actual modeling the
modeling aspect so can we create maybe
Universal models uh hierarchical models
how can we do this such that these
hierarchical models or
similar actually solve more complicated
tasks than a simple stage-based model
can
do um so for me personally I think
that's where we can
achieve the biggest gains in this
modeling part I'm not sure about what
Alber things are the most big what this
yeah what the biggest outstanding
challenge is but there are
a I I think from from yeah I totally
agree from the from the research
perspective this structural adaptation
of of the model that's the most I would
say yeah the hardest and the most
interesting uh from from my opinion
problem that's like handcrafting this
model like for for this type of drones
right it's nice can be easy sometimes
not well if you go to the
three-dimensional that gets
significantly uh more complex so indeed
like
having um a Machinery well the thing the
interesting thing that we we do have
Machinery to to do structural adaptation
uh because aren fur uh does provide the
an opportunity to extend your model to
patch it uh although how to do that in
principle how do you indeed grow or or
shrink your model and so in time while
observing and being being in the field I
think this is the most challenging part
indeed and as for well there are
certainly uh problems with uh
approximations and
um uh well uh Universal rules uh that's
something we also I think uh outline in
a few demos that well there could be a
situation where the rule for computing
the message which B showing is not is
not available uh so there is always this
question right whether you want to um
well to commit to a simpler
approximation to do it FAS or you want
to commit to a more accurate oximation
but it will take more resources uh
computational resources and how to
balance between these two that's that's
another interesting uh question how to
how to automatically decide um I think I
think this is what I would call the most
interesting uh yeah yeah
challenges I would also add from our
kind of educational and research side
that one of the big challenges
thankfully one being approached is to
devel velop the documentation and the
examples the examples help us learn but
also a lot of us are having good success
bringing in code examples into code and
language models and using the working
examples to template new examples so as
the library of open-source published
models grows that will become more
possible and then also there's a
lifelong fascinating journey of talking
about how do you go from seeing a drone
in the sky to getting those physics
equations down and that kind of like
approach to modeling and how do we get
to a graph assuming that that's where
the software package can pick up and
render it kind of no problem but there's
still this very human very collaborative
process which also could receive a lot
of documentation and examples about
getting to that kind of a
model
Chris yeah absolutely Yeah Yeah Chris do
you w to ask
anything no I just wanted to say thank
you guys very much I really enjoyed the
presentation um I liked I really enjoyed
how you broke down a lot of
the top of my head right now is like the
integration example um it it was very
intuitive it made a lot of sense and it
really highlighted a lot of the benefits
and true power in uh what you guys have
developed so thank you guys and I really
really appreciate uh your time and
explain this to
us thank you for the kind's
words if I could also add thanks for
having us one um comment just as we've
been working on it week by week a a real
like arising Insight that got us both
excited and not daunted but just
realizing the scope of the the package
and the work was in comparing the RX
confer active inference examples with
other active inference simulations like
from pmdp or built kind of custom
outside of a package like the INF for
ants examples and we realized that a lot
of alternative approaches people try to
go as fast as possible to developing an
active inference agent and then talk
about like the variational free energy
or the expected free energy of the agent
and so the package serves as a helpful
accelerator to get to an agents but
that's not like the general agents and
then even making small changes to that
scheme can be buried and Scattered
across different packages and then
there's all these other kinds of
limitations that one quickly finds thems
encountering like in the education
application settings whereas in RX and
fur it's such an engineering driven
approach so a lot of the engineers on
our team were immediately more
comfortable and then a lot of people who
had been playing with active inference
from a computer science or from a Phil
philosophical and mathematical side were
a little bit surprised because we were
getting very low level with the node
engineering and then after wiring that
up and understanding it it's just like
press play so a lot of the focus on
developing an agent was actually that
Focus was moved to better understanding
the graph that represents the ecosystem
of shared intelligence and there was
less upfront focus on merely making it
like an agent-based model because you
could make an agent-based model like the
Drone or you could develop other kinds
of graphs that don't necessarily have an
agentic basis so that helped us realize
that this is a much broader toolkit than
doing active inference or agent-based
modeling of any kind but that those are
use cases that are benefited greatly by
it definitely I think you
are actually piing the main point of our
package so RX allows us to enable or
enables us to create these agents very
quickly very adapt very efficiently so
if we compare this for example to and
you mentioned this already also from
your engineers like if you would go
through a traditional design cycle for
an engineering firm you would create a
single model kind of thingy single
algorithm let's say 50 pages or of code
or something and that's nice these 50
pages of code but all yeah it's
unmaintainable you need a lot of
Engineers to actually make improvements
upon it yeah if something
changes you know don't know what's going
to happen right whereas with rifer we
just have to specify this little piece
of code which um we which specifies the
model and then inferences automated as
you mentioned you just press play it
isn't that easy of course from the
actual engine perspective but we try to
make the user experience as good as
possible to make it as easy on the user
to build agents active inference agents
or any other applications where you
might need such Machinery to actually
complete a specific task and hopefully
by doing so by making this user
friendliness one of our priorities is we
can also enable active inference getting
adopted across Industries and across
research groups
yeah um after today if we have a quick
question is there an email that we could
send those questions
to I think there from the active
inference Institute there is an
Communication channel but Daniel please
correct me if I'm wrong directly to bias
laab but if you have questions feel free
to start a discussion on GitHub because
we actively maintain it we keep also um
a close watch on what's Happening and
there might also have been people with
similar questions before you so
my first hunch would be create a
discussion on GitHub and we will
definitely then get involved with one of
our colleagues in order to help you out
okay thanks well if if if you have
questions uh regarding uh this Dynamics
uh Venture then uh you could uh yeah use
our info ATL dynamics.com as well so
just to dump any other questions you
want yep Co well thank you all again
it's really
awesome I was thinking about how the
packages are kind of factorized and
modular and separable almost like that's
a theme that helps ecosystems work so
overall thank you very much for the work
and for presenting we've really
appreciated the chance to work with a
package in our learning groups and we'll
look forward to seeing more examples and
sharing more also from the projects that
people are working on in The
Institute thank you much was a pleasure
thank you for coming
us okay great so see you all next
time bye bye bye byee thank
youbody
for